[intense, suspenseful music playing]
[wind howling]
What's happening? Is someone attacking us?
It's Aang! He's in the Avatar State!
[whirring]
[Katara] Are you okay?
[Aang] Why didn't you stop them?
-No, I tried!
-You let them take Appa!
Aang, stop it! We barely got out of there.
-Toph did what she could.
-It wasn't enough.
-She saved us.
-I don't care.
The Earth King can help once we tell him.
[Aang] There's only one plan now.
Find Appa.
I don't care about anything else.
[Katara] We will find him.
But it's like Sokka said.
Our best chance of finding him
is going to the king.
I'm going to find Appa.
Don't wait for me. [huffs]
Aang!
[somber music playing]
Jet couldn't make it out.
It was because of him that we got away.
Aang's right.
I should've held it open longer.
You did everything you could.
[Momo chittering]
[whimpers]
[somber, dramatic music playing]
[quiet crunching]
[Aang inhales sharply]
[high-pitched whistle]
[Aang] Appa!
[echoing]
[Zuko breathing heavily]
[thunder rumbles]
[Iroh] A fever is the fire of change.
If you survive it,
it burns away your old self
and gives you new life.
[Zuko grunting]
[quirky, mysterious music playing]
[demon laughs]
[laughs]
[grunts]
[whispers] Blue Spirit.
Huh.
[demon groans]
[grunting]
[suspenseful music playing]
-[Zuko] Help! Mama!
-[Ursa] Zuko, wake up.
-[Azula screams]
-[Ursa] We need to go.
I love you so much.
No. No.
[Ursa echoing] Wake up.
-[Azula] Mama! Where's Dad?
-Wait. No.
[Ursa] Wake up.
-I won't let you turn them into monsters.
-Stop! Stop! Stop!
I… I want it to stop! Make it stop!
[in distorted voice] Is that
what you think I am? A monster?
[grunts]
Where's Dad? Where's Dad? Where's Dad?
Promise me that no matter what happens,
you stay together. Remember who you are.
Not again. Get us out of here! Move!
[Ursa] I love you so much.
-[Azula screams]
-Mom!
[Azula and Ozai] She's gone, Zuko.
She doesn't matter.
She never mattered.
You don't matter.
[Zuko panting]
[light applause]
[tense music playing]
[Ursa] He is a very sensitive being.
[Ozai] He flinches from conflict.
[Ursa] You need to give him another
chance. You need to nurture his instincts.
[Ozai] Zuko lacks strength.
[Ursa] He wants to help people.
He wants peace and justice.
[Ozai] There is a greater destiny
in store for both our children
than you can imagine.
[Ursa] They called their protector
the Blue Spirit.
[Ozai] If our son refuses
to put his younger sister in her place,
then she will take his place.
[Ursa] Zuzu,
there are no winners or losers.
[Ozai] A fight, once begun,
only ends when one wins…
[Ursa] Only those who practice courage…
[Azula screams]
[Ozai] He can be shaped.
He can be corrected.
-If our son refuses to put…
-Stop!
-[Ozai] …then she will take his place.
-[grunts]
[overlapping chatter]
-[Ursa] A monster!
-[Azula] Where's Dad?
-[Ozai] Compassion is a sign of weakness.
-[Zuko grunts]
[monster groans]
[somber music playing]
[monster purrs]
[gasps]
I'm sorry.
[rooster crows]
[uplifting music playing]
I gotta admit,
the plan isn't planning like usual.
Yeah, well, Appa was a big part of it.
I know.
He's an important member of the team.
He really carries us.
Aang's been out all night.
Should we go look for him?
-Found him!
-No.
I haven't.
[Katara] Hey.
Are you okay?
No.
Let's just figure out
how to see the Earth King.
Sokka was right.
That's the fastest way to find Appa.
Look, Aang. About what happened--
I don't wanna talk about it.
Okay. Then let's talk about the plan.
Right.
The plan. We just need to figure out
how to get through the palace guards,
the Dai Li,
and the countless impenetrable walls.
Okay, so we're walking straight
into a prison.
[Sokka] What? No.
What maniac would do that?
What do you believe you can gain
from walking into this prison?
You're the one who stands to gain.
I don't stand to gain anything.
I'm just a humble servant to the Crown.
I'll indulge your charade
if it makes you more comfortable.
I'm looking for a fugitive
from the Fire Nation.
In exchange for your…
Sorry.
…the Earth King's assistance,
I'll provide you the names of the generals
who are conspiring to discredit you.
Me?
-The cultural minister?
-[Azula] Yes.
Somehow they got the idea
that you're a sort of shadow ruler
who commands a network of spies
to maintain a chokehold
over this whole city.
And you have the names
of these conspirators?
General Sung, General Situ,
Lieutenants Khettry, Kim, and Zhang.
Very well.
I will look into your accusations
and let you know what I decide.
When?
It could take a few days or a few weeks.
You'll be dead by then.
You walk into this prison to negotiate,
immediately give up your only leverage,
and then hurl empty threats at me.
Is this what passes for military prowess
in the Fire Nation?
A few miles from here,
there are 20,000 Firebenders
who have been ordered to level the wall
and burn your city to the ground
unless I tell them to stand down.
That's what we call military prowess.
Even if that were true,
our army will handle it
like it always has.
The army whose leaders
I just named as traitors?
[Long Feng sighs]
You don't really know
who you're dealing with.
I would never put
the security of this city at risk.
I know exactly who you are.
I can see your whole history in your eyes.
You come from nothing,
so you've had to claw and connive
your way to power.
But true power,
the divine right to rule,
is something you're born with.
And were you born with it?
Or were you born second best?
You see, I know who you are too.
A privileged girl,
desperate to show that she deserves
anything.
Even in this cell, I have more power
than you could scrape together
in a thousand lifetimes
because yours is
dependent on lies and weakness
and the whims of an absent monarch.
You forget, I control the Avatar.
And he will wipe out your army
like he wiped out the armada in the North.
The Avatar is a child
who can't control his power.
In defending the North,
he destroyed the North.
He'll do the same
to your glittering metropolis.
The last thing you want
is for this to come to war.
I'm offering you a chance
to expose your enemies as traitors
and save this city.
Help me find the fugitive,
give me the Avatar,
and I will ensure
that you are recognized and rewarded
as the man who saved Ba Sing Se.
I do not make deals with the Fire Nation.
Everyone deals with the Fire Nation
one way or another.
[sizzling]
[sighs] You're up.
Yeah.
Thank you for taking care of me.
You've done the same.
I also went by work.
I missed… three shifts,
so… I got fired.
Could you still get me a job
at the tea shop?
I believe I can.
Thank you, Uncle.
Okay, how about this?
Katara creates a sudden blizzard.
[mimics wind blowing]
The guards have to go in
to get their coats.
Well, then they'll know
we have a Waterbender with us.
I still think disguising ourselves
as pillars could work.
Pillars that move?
Disguises did work
for getting into Omashu.
Okay, so then maybe we just
disguise ourselves as the Kyoshi Warriors.
-I heard they're in town.
-They are?
Yeah, I overheard someone talking about it
while I was casing the palace.
We should find them. Maybe they can help.
There's no time.
We need to figure this out now.
I've got it!
They might be expecting the four of us,
but you know who they won't be expecting?
Momo.
We hide in the bushes.
We send in Momo.
Toph and Aang can earthbend above Momo
so it looks like he can earthbend.
Well, lemurs can't earthbend.
Exactly. They'll be confused.
Therefore, distracted.
You guys have had all morning
to come up with something,
and this is the best we've got?
This is the one time
my parents could be useful.
They probably could just walk us
right through the front door.
Right through the front door.
Yeah, that's what I said.
I've got it!
[laughs] Okay.
[Toph] Did I do this?
[Aang] Sokka?
[Sokka mumbling]
Okay.
Boom!
Genius, right?
What is that?
I can't even see it,
and I already know it's bad.
I'm sure Sokka will explain it.
It's us in the casks.
-See?
-[Katara] Oh.
No.
Are you joking right now? Is he kidding?
I'm dead serious. This is what we do.
Aang and Katara get in one cask.
Me and Toph will get in the other one.
Our amazing Earthbenders
will bend in a false floor.
So we can hide under the wine.
And they'll just cart us right in.
Exactly.
[Toph] Move your hand.
No, your other hand.
[Sokka] Sorry. It's dark.
I can't see anything.
[Toph] Oh no! What a nightmare.
[Sung] Be silent.
We're approaching the palace gates.
It's not the usual palace guards.
It's the Dai Li.
General Sung.
We've been expecting you.
Yes, I have an audience
with the Earth King.
A gift from the Agrarian Zone.
Wine for the palace guards.
We'll take them from here.
Your officers must remain outside.
The cultural minister
would like to see you.
[dramatic music playing]
Hey.
[panting]
No one's gonna notice if only one of these
ends up in the storeroom, right?
I guess your little plan worked.
[Sokka grunts]
Of course it did.
My plans are foolproof. They always work.
Where's the other cask?
What?
[indistinct chatter]
Say hi!
[baby crying]
[Ying] Say hi!
Coming in, Lee?
Afraid of babies?
Huh?
You were staring out there.
Oh… no. Babies are afraid of me.
[Jin chuckles]
What do you think of the city so far?
Mmm…
It's okay, I guess.
You clearly haven't seen
all the best sites.
Um…
Uh, like, where?
Well, I could show you around a little.
Okay.
Yeah.
Thank you. All right.
Uh, Mushi. How's this?
Dragon Well tea
should be steeped at a lower temperature.
Otherwise, it could turn bitter.
I'll get rid of it.
No, no. We'll drink it.
Bitterness has its own lessons.
And once you get it right,
you can savor how far you've come.
-Let's wait a minute to be sure.
-It's clear. Let's move.
-Aang, wait.
-No.
I'm tired of waiting.
Appa needs me just as much as I need him.
I know you're upset. We all do.
And we're all here, trying to help.
But you need to get it under control.
Because if you talk
to the Earth King like this,
he's not gonna listen
to a single word we have to say.
Jet will have died for nothing.
And we won't be
any closer to finding Appa.
I'm trying.
I'm trying, okay?
I just…
I can't think straight.
I…
I miss him.
Okay? I miss him.
Aang, breathe.
[inhales deeply]
Okay.
-I'm okay.
-[Toph] Told you they'd be here.
-[Sokka] Come on. We found the study.
-[Toph] Ahem.
Toph found the study.
[Sung] Minister,
I have a meeting to get to.
Whatever this is, let's make it quick.
It's interesting
that you are so busy today,
when I also can't seem to locate
the Avatar and his companions.
He must be busy as well.
What do you want?
[Long Feng] A rumor
has come to my attention
that the military
is holding a high-level Fire Nation asset
in custody at the wall,
without informing the Crown.
This is a lie, of course,
meant to cast suspicion
on your loyalty to the Earth King.
Isn't it?
Shocking.
The lies people will tell
to undermine Ba Sing Se's security.
Uh, one more thing before you go, General.
The king has invited your daughter
to Lake Laogai.
[foreboding music playing]
Where's General Sung and the king?
We're not late, are we?
I… I don't think so.
These flowers. They had them at the party.
So?
They said they came
from the king's garden.
[King] There we go.
There we go.
[Aang] Your Majesty?
Oh.
Yes.
I'm King Kuei.
And we need to talk to you.
Oh, yes. The Avatar.
I hear you've been doing good work
in the city.
Comforting the sick. Spiritual leadership.
You're an Airbender.
Do you know the hanging gardens
of the Western Air Temple?
Yeah. I've been there.
Avatar Yangchen was actually raised there.
There's a flower there,
the silver amaranth,
that changes colors
throughout its blooming cycle.
I would give my kingdom
for the chance to see one.
[Aang] And I would love to take you there.
It's one of the most beautiful sights
in the world,
but we actually have something
we need to talk to you about.
[Sokka] A few somethings.
Serious matters, Your Majesty.
Oh.
I have people for that sort of thing.
-But if you like, I can show you around--
-We need to talk to you about the war.
Politics turns my stomach.
I haven't seen a sprite lily in a while.
You know your flora?
They're not native
to the Southern Water Tribe,
but I have a friend
who taught me a few things.
-Are you doing some weeding?
-Yes. Necessary work, but dirty.
Hmm.
The walls don't keep the weeds out,
do they, Your Majesty?
No matter how hard you might try,
everything is connected.
The weeds always find a way in.
But
with the proper help,
the flowers can thrive.
We just have to pay attention.
And take action.
I understand.
I'll hear you out.
Did you know she could do that?
So are we just waiting
to hear what this guy decides, or what?
[curious music playing]
Decision has been made for him.
He just doesn't know it yet.
He did help me realize something though.
What's that?
What I'm supposed to do.
It's the parable of the two dragons.
When the world was young
and spirits roamed free,
two dragons were born from the same egg.
Even before they hatched,
they competed for food.
One emerged, large and powerful, Hageshi.
The other,
weak and small,
Nho Xiu.
Over time,
Nho Xiu learned to fend for himself,
to hunt and scrounge in the dirt,
somehow surviving.
While Hageshi was so strong,
he could simply sit back
and steal whatever prey
his twin had hunted.
Hageshi grew so large,
he became lord of all dragons,
whether he deserved the title or not.
And the two hated each other.
One day,
Nho Xiu slaughtered a great beast.
And tired of his brother's theft, he flew
to a distant cave to eat his prize.
But Hageshi still found him
and stole the food
out of the mouth of his starving twin.
Sated,
Hageshi slept.
He was vulnerable.
It was Nho Xiu's moment to get revenge,
to take everything he'd ever wanted.
Nho Xiu hesitated for a moment
and missed his chance.
Hageshi opened his eyes
and saw his brother standing over him
with bloody intent.
Nho Xiu attacked, but it was too late.
Hageshi was ready.
He killed his brother easily.
And the smaller dragon died
full of regret
that it should come to this.
[Ty Lee] I remember this one.
My mother always said this is why
my sisters and I needed to share,
so we wouldn't kill each other.
Quaint.
But wrong.
Nho Xiu didn't regret hating his brother.
His only regret
was not killing him while he slept.
The lesson is to strike down your enemy
completely when you have the chance.
I've been sent here,
far from court, to hunt my brother.
And though he's weak, he's dangerous.
And I will not
miss my chance to kill Zuko.
[music fades]
[gentle music playing]
[indistinct chatter]
[mysterious music playing]
[Sokka] Everything we need
to defeat the Fire Nation is in there.
I can't believe
I haven't heard any of this.
Well, I heard it from Kyoshi herself.
It was in the Spirit Library.
Just trust me.
And you're proposing
that before this comet comes,
we launch a major offensive
on the Day of Black Sun?
With your help, Your Majesty,
we could save the world.
If this is true,
this may be the most important thing
I've ever heard
and the most important decision
I've ever had to make.
General Sung.
[King] General Sung, Long Feng,
I've just heard some very upsetting news.
The fall of Omashu,
an army camped outside our walls,
and a comet that will give the Firebenders
extraordinary power.
General Sung can back up
everything we've said.
Is what they say true?
-No.
-What?
Ba Sing Se is as strong as it ever was,
Your Majesty.
There are Fire Nation forces
outside our walls,
but they will be easily handled.
Kyoshi scouts have captured their general
and brought him into the city
as a prisoner.
The Avatar and his friends
simply want to feel important
in a city that does not need them.
General Sung, what are you doing?
Your Highness.
We mustn't be too hard
on the Avatar and his friends.
They're but children after all.
You can't listen to him!
He lied to me, and he's lying to you!
Aang has tried for weeks
to come here and tell you all of this.
And Long Feng has stopped him.
Interesting narrative,
coming from a thief.
Katara is no thief.
Oh, but she is.
The night of the party,
she stole some precious and valuable
golden nettles from the palace,
taking advantage
of Your Majesty's hospitality.
Since then, she has been agitating
in the Lower Ring every night,
stirring tension
in a typically peaceful place.
I was helping people who needed it.
[Long Feng] If you were being so helpful,
why did you have to don a disguise
and hide your actions?
If you were being so helpful,
why did you flee the scene of a riot?
And that's just the start.
Sources tell me
the Beifongs have been manufacturing
war machines for the Fire Nation.
War machines that they used
against the Northern Water Tribe.
War machines that they would use
against Ba Sing Se.
They are traitors to the Earth Kingdom.
That's not true.
Toph didn't know anything about that
until… until recently.
Lady Beifong is now in the city
and has been in touch with her daughter.
Who knows what young Toph
could be planning to share with her?
And this one.
This one was the last person seen
by one of the city's
most prominent thinkers
before he went missing.
The Dai Li are investigating
the disappearance of Professor Zei
as a possible murder.
Your Majesty, the Dai Li can't be trusted.
They are loyal only to Long Feng.
Keep in mind, Your Majesty,
that these accusations
are coming from a young man
who is a known collaborator with Sai,
the Fire Nation spy
who concocted this whole story.
-Sai didn't--
-What?
Didn't attempt
to assassinate the King of Omashu?
We can explain all of this.
You certainly do spin marvelous tales.
You see, Your Majesty,
the Avatar is in league
with a thief, a spy, and a traitor.
How could we possibly trust the Avatar
when his companions have shown themselves
to be enemies of the Earth Kingdom?
Please, Your Majesty,
no matter what he says about us,
it doesn't change the fact
your city's in danger.
The Fire Nation is coming,
and you have the power
to stand up and fight.
Please, Your Majesty, we need your help.
The world… needs your help.
Long Feng.
What should I do?
Don't ask him. He's a liar.
Where did you take Appa?
-Aang, don't.
-I know it was you!
[in distorted voice] Where is Appa?
-Stay back, Your Majesty.
-Aang!
[dramatic music playing]
[Katara] Aang!
[mystical whirring]
[music fades]
Escort the Avatar and his friends home.
[Katara sighs]
[somber music playing]
Thank you, Long Feng,
for your help and your loyalty.
[doors close]
I am your humble servant.
But I was never told
of these Fire Nation forces.
General Sung.
You said that part of the story was true.
Did you not?
Yes. I'll plan a visit
for you to check on our forces--
General Sung,
please send me the most recent
action reports from the wall.
Yes, Your Majesty.
And in the future,
notify me immediately and directly
of any threats to our borders.
[foreboding music playing]
[mysterious music playing]
Whatever loose hold you have on the city,
it's slipping away.
[doors open]
[doors close]
[tense music playing]
[music fades]
[Aang sighs]
Hey, we'll come up with a new plan.
We'll figure it out.
[Aang] A new plan?
It's over. We lost.
Don't say that.
And it's all your fault.
Me?
Everything was going great
up until Long Feng told the king
what you've been doing at night.
I took those nettles to help a sick kid.
Everything that I did was to help people.
Well, it didn't help us, did it?
Back off, Aang. We would've said something
if it was any of your business.
You told her about this and not me?
She didn't tell me.
I felt her leaving the house at night.
So you both lied?
No! [scoffs]
Maybe you would've felt it too
if you had focused on your earthbending
instead of running around with Long Feng.
-So much for being there for each other.
-Don't even start.
When did you find out her parents
were building weapons for the Fire Nation?
Hey, I don't have anything to do with them
anymore, so it doesn't even matter.
It matters.
How long has your family been in business
with the Fire Nation?
Do they build warships for them?
Did they build the ships
that came to Wolf Cove?
that brought Firebenders
that burned down our village
and murdered my mother?
The ones that drove our father
to abandon us?
Did they build those ships?
How could you not have told me?
I didn't even think about it.
You never do.
[Toph] Wow.
I thought that you guys understood
that I am not my family.
[Aang] Are you sure?
Because it kind of sounds like
you talk to them all the time.
-What?
-Is your mother in town?
-Yes, but--
-You didn't think we should know that?
I haven't spoken to her.
All she did was send me a letter
to tell me that she was here.
Was this before or after you found out
that she was a war criminal?
Are you kidding?
I'm not a war criminal.
[scoffs] I've been here,
helping the Avatar
get ready to fight the Fire Nation.
-Where have you been?
-Good question.
Maybe she was starting a riot.
I didn't start a riot.
Some people were attacking
innocent Fire Nation defectors.
-They were--
-Whoa! You were defending Fire Nation?
Okay. Okay, so it's fine for you.
I was defending innocent people.
It doesn't even matter what I was doing.
We know the reason this all fell apart
is Long Feng.
I knew that guy was no good
from the moment that we met him.
How was I supposed to know?
He was helping us.
Obviously, he wasn't.
-What about the people you trusted?
-Professor Zei was a real winner.
Oh yeah,
like you did any better with General Sung.
-You said she was on board.
-She was.
Then what happened?
What do you think?
-Long Feng got to her.
-Stop blaming me.
I told you you had to stay calm.
-I warned you.
-[Toph] Yeah.
Yet you had to go and fly off
into the Avatar State anyway.
[Aang] We'd already lost
after the Earth King heard
what you three had been doing.
It's like none of this matters to you.
You all act like my friends,
like you understand
the pressure I'm under, but you don't.
I have to save the world.
And you can all pretend to get it,
but you don't have any idea.
The only one who cared was Appa.
And he's gone.
Because you lost him.
Because I had to save you!
You know what?
I don't need this.
I may be blind,
but you guys don't see me at all.
-[Sokka] Hey.
-Go ahead.
Leave.
It's not like I need you anymore anyway.
[Toph scoffs]
[scoffs]
[door opens]
-You're just gonna let her go?
-You can go too if you want.
Unless you wanna sit around
and make another plan that won't work.
[Sokka] No, my plan worked fine.
We just got beat.
And that's not on me. That's on you.
So much for Team Avatar, huh?
Sokka.
[door opens]
[somber music playing]
You said you were with me.
I've always been with you.
I do everything that I can to help you.
No. You're off doing your own thing.
You don't care.
Where were you today?
I had to carry the whole team
because you were so distraught.
It was because
I made everyone focus on their jobs
that we got in front of the king
in the first place.
And that worked really great.
Didn't it?
[Katara] You know what?
Carry yourself from now on.
[door opens]
[mysterious music playing]
I can explain.
You don't have to justify
your choices to me.
I want to anyway.
I'm not doing this out of anger
or for vengeance.
I'm doing this because
I want to help people.
And
I'm doing this for myself.
[Iroh sighs]
Zuko.
I'm glad you brought me here.
You're a good man.
[uplifting music playing]
[door opens]
[door closes]
Can I help you?
I was hoping to find a friend
who still clings to the ancient ways.
[mysterious music playing]
[door closes]
I am Iroh.
Dragon of the West.
I come to offer my services.
But you knew I was here, didn't you?
[man] The Dragon of the West
is a cold-blooded killer.
He ordered the burning
of countless innocents,
the slaughter of those who would resist us
and any who would oppose
what our great nation was doing.
I'm not that man anymore.
You cannot escape the Dragon.
You and he are one and the same.
Those actions are your actions,
no matter how long you run from them.
I served under the Dragon.
I deserted the Dragon.
I left a regiment leaderless.
Many of those I abandoned perished
before the retreat was ordered.
One of them was named Lu Ten.
The Dragon would consume me
in the fire of vengeance.
What will this old man do?
[poignant music playing]
I ask your forgiveness
for the things I ordered you to do.
I forgive you.
Seconded?
-Aye.
Welcome, Iroh,
to the White Lotus.
There's work to be done.
[baby coos]
[mysterious music playing]
[woman screams]
[woman screaming]
[screams]
[suspenseful music playing]
[grunting]
[grunts]
[music swells, fades]
[knocking]
[footsteps approaching]
Toph!
Hi, Mom.
[Toph sighs]
You. [grunting]
Hi again!
I really messed everything up,
huh, Momo?
I failed
everyone.
[Momo squeaking]
[Bumi] I had to feel everything
so that I could feel nothing,
which is the key to feeling everything.
[rumbling]
[Appa grunting]
[groaning]
[Appa groans]
Appa.
[dramatic music playing]
[music fades]
c playing]